Finding Aid for the Alexander Klemin Papers LSC.0843
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alexander Klemin papers
1900-1950
UCLA Library Special Collections
Klemin, Alexander
LSC.0843
116.5 Linear Feet (233 boxes)
1 oversize_boxes (84 oversize boxes)
Alexander Klemin (1888-1950) was the head of the Aeronautics Department at MIT (1917), head of the Guggenheim School of Aeronautics at New York University's College of Engineering (1925-45), and the author of Textbook Of Aeronautical Engineering, If you Want to Fly, Simplified Aerodynamics and Airplane Stress Analysis. The collection contains correspondence, lectures, reports, designs, photographs, patents, and related printed material concerning the technical and historical aspects of aeronautics, including the development of the helicopter and the gyroscope.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. See the Existence and Location of Copies note for the link to the digitized materials.
Existence and Location of Copies
Digitized materials are available electronically at https://digital.library.ucla.edu/catalog/nf4c9000zz-89112.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Kraus Periodicals, Incorporated, purchase, 1963.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9919730043606533
Biography
Alexander Klemin was born in London, May 15, 1888; BS, London University, 1907; immigrated to the U.S., 1914; MS, Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), 1915; became a U.S. citizen while head of the Aeronautics Department at MIT, 1917; Officer-in-charge of the Research Department, Army Air Service, at McCook Field, Dayton, Ohio during World War I; head, Guggenheim School of Aeronautics at New York University College of Engineering, 1925-45; author of Textbook Of Aeronautical Engineering, If you Want to Fly, Simplified Aerodynamics, and Airplane Stress Analysis; technical editor, Aviation magazine, 1915-1917; member, Royal Aeronautical Society, American Society of Mechanical Engineers, Society of Automotive Engineers; died, 1950.
Scope and Content
Collection contains correspondence, lectures, reports, designs, photographs, patents, and related printed material concerning the technical and historical aspects of aeronautics, including the development of the helicopter and the gyroscope. The collection comprises the professional papers of Alexander Klemin as well as materials used by him as a professor. Of note is an alphabetical subject index of more than 150,000 entries to articles about helicopters, aviation, and gyroscopes in many technical journals.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Lectures file.
Helicopter file.
Technical file.
Research.
Miscellaneous.
Spin test.
Helicopter patents.
Klemin's subject index to articles in technical journals (card file).
Universities and colleges -- Faculty -- Archives.; Aeronautical engineers -- United States -- Archives.; Aeronautics -- History -- Sources.; Aerodynamics -- History -- Sources.; Klemin, Alexander, 1888-1950--Archives.
- Lectures File
  - Advanced Aerodynamics. (Box 1)
  - Advanced Aerodynamics and Advanced Structural Analysis. (Box 2)
  - Advanced Structural Analysis. (Box 3, Box 4)
  - Advanced Structural Analysis and Aerodynamics. (Box 5)
  - Aerodynamics. (Box 6)
  - Aerodynamics and Airplane Stress Analysis. (Box 7)
  - Airplane Stress Analysis. (Box 8, Box 9)
  - Airplane Stress Analysis, Airships and Autogiro. (Box 10)
  - Design. (Box 11, Box 12)
  - Design and Dynamics of Aircraft. (Box 13)
  - Dynamics of Aircraft (Longitudinal Stability). (Box 14)
  - Dynamics of Aircraft. (Box 15)
  - Dynamics of Aircraft and Modern Applied Aerodynamics. (Box 16)
  - Modern Applied Aerodynamics and Performance. (Box 17)
  - Performance. (Box 18)
  - Performance, Rotary (Autogiros), Rotary (Helicopters), and Seaplanes. (Box 19)
  - Seaplanes. (Box 20)
  - Seaplanes and Vibration. (Box 21)
- Helicopter File
  - Aircraft to Airflow. (Box 22)
  - American to Bell. (Box 23)
  - Bell to Bennett. (Box 24)
  - Bibliography to Chappedelaine. (Box 25)
  - Cierva to Cold Weather. (Box 26)
  - Convertable Aircraft to Curvilinear motion. (Box 27)
  - Dampers to Flapping Theory. (Box 28)
  - Flapping and Feathering Theory to Gearing. (Box 29)
  - General to Hohenemser. (Box 30)
  - Hoppicopter to Jet Propulsion. (Box 31)
  - Jet Propulsion to Klemmin. (Box 32)
  - Lag Hinge Theory to Los Angeles Airway. (Box 33)
  - Los Angeles Airway to Mechanisms. (Box 34)
  - Models to Performance. (Box 35)
  - Performance. (Box 36, Box 37)
  - Principles. (Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41)
  - Principles to Stress Analysis. (Box 42)
  - Stress Analysis to Student Design. (Box 43)
  - Student Design to Tower. (Box 44)
  - Sikorsky to Stability. (Box 45)
  - Stalling to Theory and Design. (Box 46)
  - Theory and Design. (Box 47)
  - Theory and Design to Transmission. (Box 48)
- Technical File
  - Acoustics: Automobiles to Acoustics: Radio. (Box 49)
  - Acoustics: Rocks to Aerodynamics: Atmosphere. (Box 50)
  - Aerodynamics: Bridge to Aerodynamics: Chimneys. (Box 51)
  - Aerodynamics: Compressible. (Box 52, Box 53)
  - Aerodynamics: Cowling to Aerodynamics: Flat. (Box 54)
  - Aerodynamics: Flutter to Aerodynamics: Fuselage. (Box 55)
  - Aerodynamics: Gasflow to Aerodynamics: Nomenclature. (Box 56)
  - Aerodynamics: Nonuniform to Aerodynamics: Rotating. (Box 57)
  - Aerodynamics: Rotating to Aerodynamics: Sails. (Box 58)
  - Aerodynamics: Sails to Aerodynamics: Subways. (Box 59)
  - Aerodynamics: Subways to Aerodynamics: Trains. (Box 60)
  - Aerodynamics: Transition to Aerodynamics: Turbulance. (Box 61)
  - Aerodynamics: Turbulance to Aerodynamics: Viscosity. (Box 62)
  - Aerodynamics: Viscosity to Aerodynamics: Vortex. (Box 63)
  - Aerodynamics: Vortex to Aerodynamics: Wake. (Box 64)
  - Aerodynamics: Absäugung to Airfoils: Data. (Box 65)
  - Airfoils: Davis to Airfoils: General. (Box 66)
  - Airfoils: Handley Page. (Box 67)
  - Airfoils: Handley Page to Airfoils: Joukowski. (Box 68)
  - Airfoils: Karman to Airfoils: Scale effects. (Box 69)
  - Airfoils: Scale Effects to Airfoils: Theory. (Box 70)
  - Airfoils: Theory to Airplane Descriptions: Boeing. (Box 71)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Bombers to Airplane Descriptions: Catalogues. (Box 72)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Cessna to Airplane Descriptions: Junkers. (Box 73)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Langley to Airplane Descriptions: Passenger. (Box 74)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Passenger to Airplane Descriptions: Ship's Fighter. (Box 75)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Shop Visits to Airplane Descriptions: Small Commercial. (Box 76)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Small Commercial to Airplane Descriptions: Sportsman. (Box 77)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Spratt to Airplane Descriptions: Training. (Box 78)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Training. (Box 79)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Training to Airplane Descriptions: Transport. (Box 80)
  - Airplane Descriptions: Transport to Airports: Economic Effects. (Box 81)
  - Airports: Equipment to Airports: Landing Leads. (Box 82)
  - Airports: Lighting to Airports: Runways. (Box 83)
  - Airports: Runways to American Bureau of Shipping: Committees. (Box 84)
  - American Bureau of Shipping: Conferences to Amphibians: Descriptions. (Box 85)
  - Amphibians: Descriptions to Army: Bids. (Box 86)
  - Army: Bids to Army Specifications. (Box 87)
  - Army: Specifications. (Box 88)
  - Army: Specifications to Army: Standards. (Box 89)
  - Army: Specifications. (Box 90, Box 91)
  - Army: Specifications to Army: Standards. (Box 92)
  - Army: Standards. (Box 93)
  - Army: Standards to Army Tactics. (Box 94)
  - Army: Tactics to Autogiros: Descriptions. (Box 95)
  - Autogriro: Design to Autogiro: Performance. (Box 96)
  - Autogiro: Performance curves to Autogiro: Stability. (Box 97)
  - Autogiro: Stability to Automobiles: American. (Box 98)
  - Automobiles: Automatic to Automobiles: Spring. (Box 99)
  - Automobiles: Streamline to Biplane Combinations: Center of Pressure. (Box 100)
  - Biplane Combinations: Experiments to Control Surfaces: Ailerons. (Box 101)
  - Control Surfaces: Ailerons to Control Surfaces: Servo. (Box 102)
  - Control Surfaces: Stability to Cooling: Heat. (Box 103)
  - Cooling: Heat to Design: Aspect Ratio. (Box 104)
  - Design: Bendix to Design: Electrical. (Box 105)
  - Design: Electric to Design: Instrument Board. (Box 106)
  - Design: Insurance View to Design: Plywood. (Box 107)
  - Design: Pressurized Cabin to Design: Skis. (Box 108)
  - Design: Spars to Design: Transport. (Box 109)
  - Design: Tricycle Landing to Design: Windshields. (Box 110)
  - Design: Wings to Dirigibles: Fabrics. (Box 111)
  - Dirigibles: General Discussion to Dirigibles: Material. (Box 112)
  - Dirigibles: Metal-clad to Dirigibles: Rigids. (Box 113)
  - Dirigibles: Records to Dynamics: Dampers. (Box 114)
  - Dynamics: Earthquakes to Dynamics: Vibration. (Box 115)
  - Dynamics: Vibration to Education: Exams. (Box 116)
  - Education: Exams to Equipment: Cameras. (Box 117)
  - Equipment: De-lcen to Floats: construction. (Box 118)
  - Floats: General to Flying: Accidents. (Box 119)
  - Flying: Assisted take-off to Flying: Night Flying. (Box 120)
  - Flying: Navigation to Flying Boats: Boeing. (Box 121)
  - Flying Boats: Description to Flying Boats: Severski. (Box 122)
  - Flying Boats: Sikorski to Full Flight: Maneuverability. (Box 123)
  - Full Flight: Manufacturers to Full Flight: Performance Tests. (Box 124)
  - Full Flight: Performance Tests to Full Flight: Safety Competition. (Box 125)
  - Full Flight: Safety Competition to Full Flight: Stability. (Box 126)
  - Full Flight: Stick Forces to Gasoline Systems: Pumps. (Box 127)
  - Gasoline Systems: Pumps to Gliders: Conferences. (Box 128)
  - Gliders: Construction to Gliders: Klemin Stories. (Box 129)
  - Gliders: Meets to Gliders: Training. (Box 130)
  - Gliders: Trains to Helicopters: D'Ascanio. (Box 131)
  - Helicopters: D'Ascanio to Helicopters: General. (Box 132)
  - Helicopters: Gyroscopic to Helicopters: Piasecki. (Box 133)
  - Helicopters: Platt to Helicopters: Theory. (Box 134)
  - Helicopters: Theory to History Dirigibles. (Box 135)
  - History: Early Pioneers to Hydrolics: Aerodynamics. (Box 136)
  - Hydrolics: Axial Flow Fan To Hydrolics: Research. (Box 137)
  - Hydrolics: Rust to Industrail Application: Mining. (Box 138)
  - Industrial Application: Newspaper to Industry: Development. (Box 139)
  - Industry: Personalities to Instruments: Altimeters. (Box 140)
  - Instruments: Altimeters to Instruments: Catalogues. (Box 141)
  - Instruments: Catalogues to Instruments: Gyroscopes. (Box 142)
  - Instruments: Hot Wire to Instruments: Tell-tale. (Box 143)
  - Instruments: Tensiometers to Instruments: Vibration. (Box 144)
  - Instruments: Vibration to Inventions: Rockets. (Box 145)
  - Inventions: Roof Landings to Klemin: Metal Construction. (Box 146)
  - Klemin: Mirror Pilot to Klemin: Trains. (Box 147)
  - Kinematics: Dynamic to Low Power Planes: Klemin. (Box 148)
  - Low Power Planes: meets to Maneuvers: Controllability. (Box 149)
  - Materials: Aluminum. (Box 150)
  - Materials: Aluminum to Materials: NonFerrous. (Box 151)
  - Materials: Non-Ferrous. (Box 152)
  - Materials: Non-Ferrous. (Box 153)
  - Materials: Non-Ferrous. (Box 154)
  - Materials: Non-Ferrous to Mathematics: Simpson's Rule. (Box 155)
  - Mathematics: Slide Rules to Mechanics of Flight:Landing. (Box 156)
  - Mechanics of Flight: Landing to Medical Aspects: Pilot Selection. (Box 157)
  - Metal construction: Stainless to Metal Construction: Substitution. (Box 158)
  - Metallurgy: Ferrous to Meteorology: Turbulence. (Box 159)
  - Meteorology: Upper Atmospehere to Motors: Auxiliary Power Units. (Box 160)
  - Motors: Balance to Motors: Compression. (Box 161)
  - Motors: Connecting Rods to Motors: Cycles. (Box 162)
  - Motors: Cyclone to Motors: Description. (Box 163)
  - Motors: Description to Moters: Diesels. (Box 164)
  - Motors: Diesels. (Box 165)
  - Motors: Diesel to Motors: Fatigue. (Box 166)
  - Motors: Fins to Motors: Fuels. (Box 167)
  - Motors: Fuels to Motors: General. (Box 168)
  - Motors: German to Intercoolers. (Box 169)
  - Motors: Intercooler to Motors: Laboratories. (Box 170)
  - Motors: Liquid Cooling to Motors: Master Rods. (Box 171)
  - Motors: Materials to Motors: Pratt & Whitney. (Box 172)
  - Motors: Power Plant to Motors: Submerged Engine. (Box 173)
  - Motors: Supercharging to Motors: Two-cycle. (Box 174)
  - Motors: Turbine to Naval Architecture: Ship Resistance. (Box 175)
  - Naval Architecture: Skin Friction to Navy: Weight Statement. (Box 176)
  - New York University: Reprints to Performance Calculations: Controllable. (Box 177)
  - Performance Calculations: Corrections to Photographs: Aerodynamics. (Box 178)
  - Photographs: Airplanes. (Box 179)
  - Photographs: Airplanes to Photographs: Airships. (Box 180)
  - Photographs: Airship Accessories to Photographs: Engines. (Box 181)
  - Photographs: Factories to Photographs: Landing Gear. (Box 182)
  - Photographs: Landing Field to Photographs: Passenger Compartment. (Box 183)
  - Photographs: Personalities to Photographs: Safety Competition. (Box 184)
  - Photographs: Safety Competition to Photographs: Transportation. (Box 185)
  - Photographs: Transportation to Propellers: Controllable Pitch. (Box 186)
  - Propellers: Counter to Propellers: Magnesium. (Box 187)
  - Propellers: Maintenacne to Propellers: Stress Analysis. (Box 188)
  - Propellers: Submerged Engine to Propellers: Variable Pitch. (Box 189)
  - Propellers: Variable Pitch to Propellers: Windmills. (Box 190)
  - Propellers: Windmills to Radio: Traffic Control. (Box 191)
  - Research: Aerodynamics to Sand Testing: Complete Machine. (Box 192)
  - Sand Testing: Complete Machine to Seaplanes: Take off. (Box 193)
  - Shop Process: Bag Moulding to Shop Process: Pressing. (Box 194)
  - Shop Process: Photographic Methods to Shop Process: Welding. (Box 195)
  - Shop Process: Wood Shop to Stability: Electrical Solution. (Box 196)
  - Stability: Flying Qualities to Stability: Operations. (Box 197)
  - Stability: Polynomial Equasions to Stability: Stabilizers. (Box 198)
  - Stability: Stabilizers to Strength of Materials: Columns. (Box 199)
  - Strength of Materials: Continous Beam to Strength of Materials: Plastic Bodies. (Box 200)
  - Strength of Materials: Plasticity to Strength of Materials: Welded Joints. (Box 201)
  - Strength of Materials: Wheels to Stress Analysis: Chassis. (Box 202)
  - Stress Analysis: Columns to Stress Analysis: Cylinders. (Box 203)
  - Stress Analysis: Door Stresses to Stress Analysis: General. (Box 204)
  - Stress Analysis: German Methods to Stress Analysis: Moment Distribution. (Box 205)
  - Stress Analysis: Monocoque to Stress Analysis: Reduced Modules. (Box 206)
  - Stress Analysis: Research to Stress Analysis: Skin. (Box 207)
  - Stress Analysis: Skin to Stress Analysis: Stress Ratios. (Box 208)
  - Stress Analysis: Striners to Stress Analysis: Variable Moment of Inertia. (Box 209)
  - Stress Analysis: V.G. Diagrams to Testing of Materials: Thermo-elasticity. (Box 210)
  - Testing of Materials: Toughness of Wood to Transportation: Cargo Handling. (Box 211)
  - Transportation: Communications to Transportation: Feeder Line. (Box 212)
  - Transportation: Financial Analysis to Wind Tunnel Operation: Supersonic. (Box 213)
- Research
  - Plywood. (Box 214)
  - Plywood and Miscellaneous. (Box 215)
  - Automatic Pilot and Miscellaneous. (Box 216)
  - Wood Construction and Miscellaneous. (Box 217)
  - Wind Tunnel and Miscellaneous. (Box 218)
- Miscellaneous
  - Ranger Aircraft Engine Installation Manual and Princeton Univ. Preliminary Reports on Blades. (Box 219)
  - Uncategorized. (Box 220, Box 221)
- Spin Test
  - Flat Spin. (Box 222)
  - Dynamics of Spin and Spin Balance. (Box 223)
  - Spin Balance and Spin Reports. (Box 224)
  - Spin Reports and Miscellaneous. (Box 225)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 226)
- Helicopter Patents
  - May 21, 1861-July 6, 1915. (Box 227)
  - July 6, 1915-June 20, 1935. (Box 228)
  - July 14, 1925-October 22, 1931. (Box 229)
  - December 1, 1931-July 24, 1934. (Box 230)
  - August 21, 1934-May 8, 1938. (Box 231)
  - and Unassociated Patents., March 22, 1938-December 25, 1944 (Box 232)
  - Letters, photographs, etc. (Box 233)
  - Photographs, ephemera, research material, etc. (Box 234, Box 235)
- Klemin's Subject Index to Articles in Technical Journals
  - Index to Subject Headings. (Box 236)
  - A - Acoustics. (Box 237)
  - Acoustics - aerodynamics. (Box 238)
  - Aerodynamics. (Box 239, Box 240, Box 241, Box 242)
  - Aerodynamics - Airfoils. (Box 243)
  - Airfoils. (Box 244, Box 245, Box 246)
  - Airfoils - Airplane description. (Box 247)
  - Airplane description. (Box 248, Box 249, Box 250, Box 251)
  - Airplane description - Airports. (Box 252)
  - Airports - Army bombing. (Box 253)
  - Army bombing - authors. (Box 254)
  - Autogyros - balloons. (Box 255)
  - Balloons - Commerce Department. (Box 256)
  - Commerce Department - control surfaces. (Box 257)
  - Control surfaces - cooling. (Box 258)
  - Cooling - design. (Box 259)
  - Design. (Box 260, Box 261, Box 262)
  - Design - dirigibles. (Box 263)
  - Dirigibles. (Box 264)
  - Drawing office data - dynamics. (Box 265)
  - Dynamics - floats. (Box 266)
  - Floats - flying. (Box 267)
  - Flying. (Box 268)
  - Flying - flying boats. (Box 269)
  - Flying boats - full flight. (Box 270)
  - Full flight - gliders. (Box 271)
  - Gliders - helicopters. (Box 272)
  - Gliders - helicopters. (Box 273)
  - Helicopters. (Box 274)
  - Helicopters - history. (Box 275)
  - History - hydraulics. (Box 276)
  - Hydraulics - industrial application. (Box 277)
  - Industrial applications - inspections. (Box 278)
  - Inspections - instruments. (Box 279)
  - Instruments. (Box 280)
  - Instruments - low power planes. (Box 281)
  - Low power planes - materials. (Box 282)
  - Materials. (Box 283)
  - Materials - mathematics. (Box 284)
  - Mechanics - metal construction. (Box 285)
  - Metal construction - meteorology. (Box 286)
  - Meteorology - motors. (Box 287)
  - Motors. (Box 288, Box 289, Box 290, Box 291, Box 292, Box 293)
  - Motors - Navy. (Box 294)
  - Navy - performance calculations. (Box 295)
  - Performance calculations - post office. (Box 296)
  - Post office - propellers. (Box 297)
  - Propellers. (Box 298)
  - Propellers - radio. (Box 299)
  - Radio - research. (Box 300)
  - Research - sea planes. (Box 301)
  - Sea planes - shop processes. (Box 302)
  - Shop processes - stability. (Box 303)
  - Stability. (Box 304, Box 305)
  - Stability - strength. (Box 306)
  - Strength - stress. (Box 307)
  - Stress. (Box 308, Box 309, Box 310)
  - Stress - testing. (Box 311)
  - Testing - transportation. (Box 312)
  - Transportation. (Box 313, Box 314)
  - Transportation - wind tunnel abrasion. (Box 315)
  - Wind tunnel abrasion. (Box 316)
  - Wind tunnel abrasion - Z. (Box 317)